The library of the castle Mikulov
The castle Mikulov
The library of the castle Mikulov
late 13th - 16th centuries
CZ CZ-1 121
The castle Mikulov
To 30 manuscripts
The castle Mikulov Zámek 1 Mikulov Czech Republic 692 15 http://www.rmm.cz
The castle Mikulov
The Swedes drag the original library of Diterichstein “the Cardinal's” founded by Adam of Dietrichstein and increased by Cardinal František of Dietrichstein off to the Stockholm in 1645 and it enriched the library of the Quin Kristina. She gave the most famous books to the library of Vatican (Codices Reginenses). Thanks B. Dudík 21 manuscripts ware given back from Stockholm to Moravia. The foundation of the present collection of castle was the family library of Hofmann of Grünbüchel, came from Štýrsko and moved to Moravia in 1568, the library was moved to Mikulov in 1688. The founder of library of Hofmann was Bedřich Hofmann of Grünbüchel (died before 1533). But the library was the most enriched thanks Ferdinand (1540 – 1607) he gained for example the collections of German humanist Hieronym Münzer von Feltkirch (1469 – 1529). The present library is the remnant of a large library that once included the libraries of Janov, Rabštejn, Silesian, Brno and Olomouc. The library was acquired by Ferdinand of Dietrichstein (1636 – 1698); after his death, it returned to the family of Hofmann, who then moved the collections to the Mikulov in 1688. The second basic collection of the library was the family library of Pruskovský' of Pruskov, the Dietrichsteins gained the library thanks to inheriting it. The next additions of the library of Mikulov came in the end of the 19th century when the libraries of Vincence Weintridt (1778 – 1849) were added; he was a representative of the Enlightenment; the French and Germany books from the castle in Libochovice in 1859. The library gained the library of Piaristic gymasium in Mikulov and the library of prof. Halaška (1780 – 1847, professor in Piarists gymnasium in Mikulov) in the end of the 19th century; the private library of prince Alexandr Dietrichstein-Mensdorff- Pouill (1813 – 1871). The library was in auction in 1953 and a lot of unique books was sold out. Some of the sold books gains Dr. Kruliš – Randa to his collection. Later they moved to the National Museum in Prague. The state of Czechoslovakia bought 117 manuscripts and 208 early prints, placed in the Library of University in Brno. The rest of the library was moved stand in castle to the 1945 and then moved to the administration of the Okresní archiv in 1947. Except the major library the library has next 6 collections: the librariy of Weintridt, Piaristic, Halaškov, Alexandr of Dietrichstein, Libochovice and personal library of Dietrichsteins.
<ul> <li>The library has a series of catalogues; the oldest catalogue comes from the late 16th - 18th centuries (sign. 1418). The list of manuscripts made Antonin Brun in 1881 - 1882.</li> <li>http://www.rmm.cz</li> </li>
- A codex with theological texts, the turn of the 13th and 14th century; sign. 6365; 1 manuscript, parchment, 225 ff; manuscript binden in 1587, on the boards supralibros Ferdinand Flofrnann of Grünbiüchl
  <ol> <li>Petrus Pictaviensis, Compendium historiae Veteris ac Novi testamenti (Arbor historiae biblicae)</li> <li>Guilelmus Autissiodorensis, Summa super quattuor libros Sententiarum sive Summa aurea, lib. 2nd – 4th</li> </ol>
- Niketas de Herakleia (?), Synagógé tón eis to kata Joannén theion euangelion diaforon exegéseón, 1565 - 1575; sign. 6370; 1 manuscript, 507 ff, manuscript binden in 1588, supralibros Ferdinand Hofmann z Griünbüchl
- A codex with theological texts, 1397; sign. 6363; 1 manuscript, 224 ff
  <ol> <li>Bernhardus Clarevallensis, Homiliae de S. Maria</li> <li>Thomas de Aquino, De decem praeceptis</li> <li>Mattheus de Cracovia, Postilla de sanctis et de commune sanctorum</li> <li>Bertoldus Rusticanus de Ratispona, Sermones de sanctis et de angelis</li> </ol>
- A codex with theolgical and sermonical texts, 1399; sign. 6589; 1 manuscript
  <ol> <li>Henricus de Frimaria: De decem praeceptis</li> <li>Guillelmus de Lavicea: Dieta salutis</li> <li>Sermones</li> </ol>
- The Missale, turn of the 14th and15th century; sign. 6391; 1 manuscript, parchment, fragment, 4 ff
- A codex with theological texts, early 15th century; without sign.; 1 manuscript, 137 ff
  <ol> <li>Pseudo Innocencius IV: Summa poenitentia</li> <li>Johannes de Deo: Liber poenitentiaris</li> <li>Libellus dispensationum</li> <li>Stephanus de Rudnitz: Quaestiunculae</li> </ol>
- The Postilas, 1410 - 1420; sign. 6368; 1 manuscript, 212 ff
  <ol> <li>Postilla de tempore, pars hiemalis (beginning missing)</li> <li>Albertus de Padua, Postilla de tempore, pars hiemalis</li> </ol>
- Floretus, 1416; sign. 6373; 1 manuscript, 509 ff
  f. 299rb: <q>Explicit liber utilis valde, nomine Floretus nuncupatus, collectus ex diversis libris sacre theologie, finitus anno Domini M<sup>o</sup>CCCC<sup>o</sup>XVI<sup>o</sup>, feria IIIo ante festum venerabilis Galli.</q>
- A Postila, early 15th century; sign. 6395; 1 manuscript, beginning and end missing; as endpapers is used “binio kopiář” with copy of a document from 19th century and notarial instrument by Jan Schechteler of Hombergu: the regulation of the Pope Martin V. from 1426
- Tabulae computisticae; Cruciferus Gaerparus, Canones tabularum...; Gallus de Monte Sion (?), Instrumentum..., 1470 - 1480; sign. 6361; 1 manuscript, 171 ff
  <ol> <li>Tabulae computisticae</li> <li>Cruciferus Gaerparus: Canones tabularum ad meridianum Wratislaviensem et ad meridianum Pragensem</li> <li>Gallus de Monte Sion (?): Instrumentum quadrati geometrici</li> </ol>
- A codex with theological texts, 1475; sign. 6369; 1 manuscript, 276 ff
  <ol> <li>Dionysos Aeropagita: De ecclesiastica hierarchia</li> <li>Dionysos Aeropagita: De mystica theología</li> <li>De communione</li> <li>Augustinus Aureliensis: Sermones</li> <li>Albertus Magnus: Summa de officio missae</li> <li>Albertus Magnus: Summa de Corpore Domini</li> <li>Radbertus Paschasius</li> <li>De corpore et sanguine Domini</li>
- Quaestiones theologicae; Sermones; Tractatus de cesura ecclesiastica, late 15th century; sign. 6372; 1 manuscript
  <ol> <li>Quaestiones theologicae</li> <li>Sermones</li> <li>Tractatus de cesura ecclesiastica</li> </ol>
- Super Aristotelis Fysica commentarius, Waltheri Burley libri quattuor, 15th century; sign. 6378; 1 manuscript